Good morning, my name is Dan Margulies. Today's the 23rd day of
תמוז Tammuz and we are on נדרים מז. Nedarim Mem Zayin. I'm
filling in for Rabbi Lindzer while he is on vacation. Okay. So
the case that we start right at the top of מז Mem
Zayin is the case from the משנה. Mishnah. A person says, אומר
לחברו ביתך,
Omer le-chavero
beitecha, right,
against ביתך.
beitecha. Right. Again, ביתך. beitecha. So if a person says that he
takes a נדר, neder, אומר לחברו קונם לביתך שאני נכנס, Omer le-chavero
Konam le-beitecha she-ani nichnas, that your house is forbidden to me by
קונם, Konam, that I won't go into it, or שדך שאני לוקח.
Sadecha she-ani lokeiach. מת או שמכרו לאחר מותר. Meis o she-macharo le-acher
mutar. If he died, meaning the owner, or he sold it to
a third party, then it is permitted because the לשון lashon of
the נדר neder was precisely לביתך, le-beitecha, that it is your house.
But since it's no longer his house if he dies or sells
it, then the נדר neder would no longer apply to that house.
However, if he says קונם בית זה שאני נכנס, Konam bayit zeh
she-ani nichnas, that this house is forbidden to me,
מת או שמכרו לאחר אסור. meis o she-macharo le-acher asur. If he
dies or sells it to someone else, then it is forbidden.
Didn't
we have a case very similar to this last week?
Yes, this משנה Mishnah was quoted in the גמרא Gemara last week.
Oh, got it. Okay. So now we're actually getting into the גמרא
Gemara on this case. And so just to point one thing which
we mentioned yesterday which comes up in the רן Ran here actually
on מז Mem Zayin is that the רן Ran notes the fact
that each of these cases, ביתך beitecha and בית זה, bayit zeh,
each have their own חומרות chumrot for different הלכות. halachot. So for
example, our משנה Mishnah is noting the fact that בית זה, bayit
zeh, this house, is more חמור, chamur, it has a stricter הלכה
halacha regarding if the person, the owner, dies or sells it, that
it would still remain forbidden because the object itself was made אסור
asur rather than the object vis-a-vis its relationship to its owner. And
therefore, if it changes ownership, it remains forbidden. However, the רן Ran
says ביתך חמור לענין נפילה. beitecha chamur le-inyan nefilah. The saying your
house is stricter regarding what if the house falls down and is
then rebuilt. That when you rebuild a new house in the same
place, that the נדר neder would still apply to the new house.
However, בית זה, bayit zeh, this house, כיון דנפל אזלא. keivan de-nafal
azla. Once it falls down, it's gone, it's done. What if it's
my house, but
the
new house is my house too?
Right, the new house is my house or his house, but the
old house is gone and there's a new house.
It's like you have these laws, like you know, it's still considered
to be like the old house if you leave the basement, so
for tax purposes.
Oh, that's interesting.
Yeah, so if you completely also demolish the basement even though you're
building completely exactly on the same plot of land, then it's a
totally new house and it can be reassessed at a higher rate.
But you know, if not...
Well, I think some of that actually comes up when you're talking
about נגעים, Nega'im, צרעת. Tzara'at. If the house gets נגעים, Nega'im, then
how much of the house do you have to knock down? Things
like that. And for permit also, how much of it has to
fall down? For sure. And again with property rights and the house
that's built next to a temple of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and
you have to knock down which wall and things like that.
Yeah, there's actually a curious issue in places like California where they
assess new property completely different from old property.
So that's also again for tax purposes and thing like that. Two
other bits of tangential topics related to this question of the house
falling down. The first is the question of שברי כלים. shivrei keilim.
If you have vessels, containers, which are טמאים, tameim, they are impure,
and they break, then usually broken כלים, keilim, שברי כלים, shivrei keilim,
are, they become טהור. tahor. However, the Rabbis instituted for certain kinds
of כלים, keilim, particularly metal כלים, keilim, that if you remake the
vessel out of the broken vessel, if you put it back together
in some way, they instituted טומאה ישנה. tumah yeshanah. The old טומאה
tumah should continue or be reinstated
in this newly remade vessel because they were concerned that people would
say, oh, metal is easy to forge, I'll break it intentionally, it'll
become טהור, tahor, and then I'll just smelt it back together again,
I'll solder it or whatever it is, and the pieces will come
back together, and that would be easier than dealing with the טומאה
tumah the classical way, either in the מקוה mikveh or with the
ashes of פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So in a certain sense, that's
also a discussion about how much when you remake something is it
really a continuation of the old object or is it a new
object? It sounds like דאורייתא...
d'Oraita... It's easier to put in a metal כלים keilim in the
מקוה mikveh than to melt it all down again.
Well, perhaps you don't have a מקוה. mikveh. And the example specifically
is actually talking about טומאת מת tumat meis where you would need
the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, you'd have to go to Jerusalem or
whatever. So here, it would be much easier just to take it
to your blacksmith and he'll fix it up real quick.
Okay, I don't know my local blacksmith.
Well, nowadays, you know, we have changes in technology, we don't have
local blacksmiths anymore. The other example is a גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* from
סוכה *Sukkah* כ״ז *chaf-zayin*, and that's dealing with the position of רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* holds that the סוכה *sukkah*
you use on סוכות *Sukkot* must be a סוכה *sukkah* that is
ראויה לכל שבעה *re'uyah lekol-shivah*. It has to be usable for all
seven days of סוכות *Sukkot*. So what happens then if your סוכה
*sukkah* falls down in the middle of סוכות *Sukkot* and then you
rebuild it? So that's a big problem for רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
who in a certain sense must be able to hold that position
because otherwise what סוכה *sukkah* are you going to sit in? If
it falls down it's an אונס *onus*, you're totally, totally not your
fault.
Not ראויה *re'uyah*, but just an אונס *onus* made it fall down.
So, okay, so what, so but again, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
asks this question on רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s position, says האי אחריתי
היא ואינה לשבעה *hai achrisha hi ve-einah le-shivah*. If it falls down
and you had to rebuild it, it's a totally new סוכה *sukkah*
and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses another source and says קא
משמע לן *ka mashma lan* really that even according to רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* that would still be suitable and תוספות *Tosfos* there has
a suggestion that you may have to rebuild it using the same
materials, that even according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s position, even though
you have a dispensation in case of אונס *onus* and the fact
like okay it broke, you still have to sit in the סוכה
*sukkah*, but תוספות *Tosfos* says you might have to use the same
wood. So that might make it enough of the same, the same
סוכה *sukkah* the same way we're talking about here of the same
house when you rebuild it. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
asks a question on this case from the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah*: אמר
Amar, לך חברו *Amar lecha chavero*. So a person says to his
friend, this is talking about the case of the house, אבימי *Avimi*.
So אביי אבימי *Abbaye Avimi*? אבימי *Avimi* asks: קונם konam. לבית זה
שאתה נכנס *Konam labayit zeh she'atah nichnas*. What about not if a
person makes himself אסור Assur *assur* to your house, a person telling
his friend I'm אסור asur *assur* to enter into your house, what
about קונם konam לבית זה *konam labayit zeh* this house?
Presumably
it must be my house because why? Because אין אדם אוסר דבר
שאינו שלו Ein Adam Oser Davar She'eino Shelo, *ein adam oser davar
she'eino shelo*. A person cannot make someone else's property forbidden to someone
else. You can affect your own status regarding your own property, you
can affect your own status for someone else's property, and you can
affect someone
else for your property, but you can't change his relationship to his
property. So it must be קונם לבית זה *konam labayit zeh* really
meaning ביתי Beiti *beiti* שאתה נכנס *she'atah nichnas*. He's trying to forbid
his friend to go into his house. Okay. מת או שמכרו לאחר
מהו *Met o she-mecharo le-acher mahu*? So what about if a person,
that person, the owner dies, the person who made the נדר Neder
*neder* dies, or sells it to someone else? מהו *Mahu*? So the
question is: אדם אוסר דבר שברשותו לכשיצא מרשותו או לא *Adam oser
davar she-birshuto lichshe-yeitzei me-reshuto o lo*? Can a person forbid something which
is in his possession
even after it leaves his possession? Meaning right now you have control
over your property, you can make this נדר Neder *neder*, but similarly
to the question we asked before that if the owner sells the
house does that then remove it from its נדר Neder, *neder*, so
too can you, can your נדר neder, *neder* make this house forbidden
to someone else even after it leaves your possession or not? Right
now I'm in control of it, I take a נדר neder *neder*
and it creates this prohibition. Now if I die or if I
sell the house then does that prohibition still remain? Did it change
the nature of the house or was it sort of always continuing
because it was mine but now that it's no longer mine the
prohibition is gone? So רבא Rava *Rava* has an answer. אמר רבא
Amar Rava. *Amar Rava*: תא שמע *Ta shema*. האומר לבנו קונם שאתה
נהנה meheneh לי *Ha-omer livno konam she-ata neheneh li*. במת ירשנו
*Bemet yirashenu*. Okay, so we have now from בבא קמא Bava Kamma.
*Bava Kamma*: A person says to his son a נדר neder, *neder*
קונם שאתה נהנה meheneh לי *konam she-ata neheneh li* you cannot benefit
me and then he dies, ירשנו *yirashenu*, he can inherit from him.
Why? Because by the time the father dies he's no longer the
father, he's not really a real person at that point and so
the ירושה yerusha. *yerusha*, the inheritance is not his property anymore, it's
sort of already left the father's property and the son could inherit.
But what if he says בחיי ובמותי *be-chayai uve-moti* in the לשון
Lashon *lashon* of the נדר neder *neder* he says while I am
alive and while I once I die, then במת *bemet*, if he
dies, לא ירשנו *lo yirashenu*, because the explicit mention of that this
prohibition should last even after I die would prevent the son from
deriving the benefit from it after the father dies.
Okay. That's disinherited. Well, to a certain extent it's taking a נדר
neder, *neder* to disinherit. The ר״ן *Ran* has a few problems with
this. Yeah. Okay.
So you have to,
so basically when you say לבית זה *labayit zeh* you would have
to have said בחיי ובמותי *be-chayai uve-moti* then that would work. If
you just said לבית זה *labayit zeh* but
not say now and forever then that's the answer to our question
right? Just...
Okay, so part of it is how much is sort of implicit
in the לשון *lashon* of the נדר neder *neder* or not, how
much has to be made explicit, but רבא Rava *Rava*'s proof, רבא
Rava *Rava* says right שמע מינה אדם אוסר דבר שברשותו לכשיצא מרשותו
*shma mina adam oser davar she-birshuto lichshe-yeitzei me-reshuto*. You a person still
has this legal power. A person has the power to create a
prohibition. Only perhaps only if you're explicit about it. That's the case.
That's the proof. Okay, so אבימי *Avimi*'s question still has a good
answer, meaning the the legal principle applies. The case that אבימי *Avimi*
was talking about where he didn't mention it explicitly maybe wouldn't work,
but it would work in another case. A few problems. Number one
problem is that the רן Ran *Ran* and the רשבא Rashba *Rashba*
disagree about whether there is זכיה באיסורי הנאה hana'ah *zechia b'issurei hana'ah*.
Can you really gain ownership of something which is אסור בהנאה assur
be-hana'ah. *assur b'hana'ah* that you can't get הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* from? The
רן Ran *Ran* thinks, yeah, you could own it. You're allowed to
own property even if it's אסור asur *assur*. Yeah, I own cheese.
So that's not אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah. *assur b'hana'ah*, it's just אסור
asur באכילה *assur b'achila*. Different, right?
Well, okay, so, well,
cheeseburger
could be אסור בהנאה assur be-hana'ah. *assur b'hana'ah*. Why? If they're really
cooked together or, you know, things like that. There are three prohibitions,
איסור Issur חלב *issur chalav*, איסור Issur. הנאה hana'ah *issur hana'ah*, איסור
אכילה *issur achila*, and איסור בישול *issur bishul*.
So the רן Ran *Ran* says,
to mean if I went to buy cheeseburger I can't because of
אין זכיה באיסורי הנאה hana'ah *ain zechia b'issurei hana'ah*?
Let's talk more about the inheritance. You know, this is the question
of for example, I mean we get into this later on as
well with dividing inheritance. A person is a convert who's a child
of an idol worshiper, and the idol worshiper owns all sorts of
עבודה זרה *avoda zara* and things like that. Can he then go
to his siblings and divide up the inheritance such that you
take the עבודה זרה *avoda
zara* and I'll take the house and things like that? So those
are questions involved with this as well, and the רן Ran *Ran*
thinks, yeah, you could own it as long as you're not getting
הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* from it. The רן *Ran* also has a problem
because in בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*, the סוגיא *sugya* that this comes
up in in בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*, he says really fine, so
the son can't inherit it, but he could then pass it on
to his children, to the grandson.
So the son can't inherit? That's what, so how can he pass
it on to anybody?
לא ירשנו *lo yerishenu*. Ah, so that's also the question because that
sounds like טובת הנאה hana'ah *tovat hana'ah*, right? The fact that you
can tell which of your grandkids to give it to or something
like that, that that would be, of your your children, meaning the
grandchildren of the person who died, then that sounds like טובת הנאה
hana'ah *tovat hana'ah*, that you're you're benefiting the relationship in some way
that these people would be interested in in receiving it.
Yeah, not even that, but separating the question of benefit, how can
you pass something on that you don't own?
So again, you sort of have some kind of, again, this is
because the רן *Ran* is saying that you can own it. The
רן *Ran* says you could own it, you just can't get a
benefit from it. So you couldn't then sell it or you couldn't
use it.
Which case are we talking about the house?
The case where it says לא ירשנו *lo yerishenu*. The case where
the father took a נדר neder *neder* that the son cannot get
benefit from him and then dies, and the son now is standing
to inherit the property of the father.
Does he say inherit or does he say benefit or inherit?
So he says you cannot benefit from me, שאי אתה נהנה לי
*she-ee-attah neheneh li*, or right, so who's benefiting whom exactly is also
again the לשון *lashon* of the נדר neder. *neder* again becomes the
confusing, but the context says that the son shouldn't be allowed to
get benefit from the father. Yes?
Can you make a נדר neder *neder* which proscribes a הלכה Halacha
דאורייתא *halakha d'oraita*?
How dare you ask that.
Okay, so that's interesting. Perhaps he has other sons. Perhaps because it's
general, right? You can't get any הנאה hana'ah. *hana'ah* at all, a
general a general prohibition, no הנאה hana'ah, *hana'ah* at all, then the
inheritance falls into it. So maybe that's a different rule than just
saying you can't get the inheritance should be קונם *konam* to you
would be a bit different because maybe that's really is exactly overlaying
on the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. But here it's a more general prohibition
than just the inheritance. Extra words around. There are well there are
workarounds for those kinds of things.
Oh wait wait, I'm sorry, so you were saying that in this
case although the son can't inherit, he can still pass it on
to his children?
So that's what the רן *Ran* brings that from בבא קמא *Bava
Kamma*, and that becomes kind of problematic for how does this סוגיא
*sugya* then work? Okay, maybe we keep going with this.
Fine. Okay.
Oh but wait, can you say something like, in other words, can
I say something like this: so let's say you have a house,
right? Okay. And I don't have it yet, but can I say
to David, if I ever get this house, it's אסור asur הנאה
hana'ah *assur hana'ah* for you. Can I do that?
If I
ever buy this house, you can't have הנאה hana'ah *hana'ah* from me.
When I say that it's not mine.
Okay, so we're going to get to that in the next עמוד
*amud* which is a question of דבר שלא בא לעולם Davar Shelo
Ba Le'olam. *davar shelo ba l'olam*, דבר שלא בא לעולם Davar Shelo
Ba Le'olam, *davar shelo ba l'olam*. So that's we're getting to it
in just a few minutes. It's a good question. Okay.
Two other points about this before we go on to the next
piece. Number one is that רב חיים *Rav Chaim* notes the difference
between הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* and נדרים Nedarim *nedarim*. Here we said that
part of this question about אדם אוסר דבר שברשותו לכשיצא מרשותו *adam
oser davar shebirshuto lechsheyetzei mershuto*, a person can forbid something which is
currently in his possession even once it leaves his possession. So what's
the difference between הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* and נדרים Nedarim. *nedarim*? הקדש Hekdesh
*hekdesh* according to רב חיים *Rav Chaim* really does change the object,
the object by itself. It doesn't matter who owns it, it doesn't
matter where it is or what your relationship to it is, הקדש
Hekdesh *hekdesh* is just a status in the object totally. And even
though by נדרים nedarim, *nedarim*, נדרים Nedarim *nedarim* that we say are
always focused on the object, it's חפצא חפצא חפצא *cheftza cheftza cheftza*,
it's just about the status of the object really, נדרים Nedarim. *nedarim*
really does care about the status of the. relationship of the object
to you. Right, that's part of this אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו
שלו, Ein Adam Osser Davar She'eino Shelo, a person can't forbid something
that's not his own property, how it relates to you, and these
סוגיות Sugyas here are about what if conditional in the לשון of
the נדר neder was the fact that it belongs to a certain
person. So that's just a difference between הקדש Hekdesh and
the way הקדש Hekdesh is written, I can't be מקדיש Makdish דבר
שאינו שלו Davar She'eino Shelo either.
You can't either because you don't have rights over it, so that's
because you don't, you can't have control of the object. But for
anything that you have the power to create the הקדש Hekdesh, status,
there's no saying ביתך Beitecha is הקדש or ביתי is הקדש and
then you try to sell it in between and that would somehow
remove. Again, it's just, part of it may also be, הקדש is
at one point in time. At one point in time you create
this status and that's good for forever. And with נדרים nedarim because
it's connected to the original נודר, Noder, so it's sort of continually
renewing itself and that's at least the question about אדם אוסר דבר
שיבא לרשותו. Adam Oser Davar Shebishelichsheyavo Lereshuso. If it, once it leaves
your possession, maybe the נדר neder wouldn't work anymore because you don't
have power over it anymore. But so we at least רבא brings
a proof that it still would work.
Okay. The גמרא, Gemara. תנן התם. Tnan Hatam. Okay, a new case.
We have now from later on in the מסכתא. Masechta. קונם פירות
האלו עלי. Konam Peirot Ha'eilu Alai. A person says these fruits are
אסור asur to me with a נדר, neder or קונם הם על
פי, Konam Hem Al Pi, they are forbidden to my mouth, קונם
הם לפי, Konam Hem Lefi, or they are forbidden to my mouth.
So either לפי Lefi or על פי, Al Pi, on my mouth
or in my mouth, אסור בחילופיהן ובגידוליהן. Assur Bechilufeihen Uviggiduleihen. They are
forbidden and חילופיהן, Chilufeihen, if you try to sell the fruit, then
the money that you get is forbidden as well.
Sounds like sort of again like the world of קרבנות, Korbanot, תמורה
Temura והקדש. V'Hekdesh.
And גידוליהן, Giduleihen, and if you would plant the seeds from the
fruit and then they grow new fruit trees and you harvest those
fruits, then those are also forbidden. Something else similar you mentioned about
הקדש, also תרומה. Terumah. We have a concept of גידולי תרומה, Gidulei
Terumah, that if you plant the fruits of תרומה, Terumah, I forget
now whether גידולי תרומה Gidulei Terumah are מדרבנן Midrabanan or מדאורייתא, Mid'oraita,
but the fruits that grow out of the תרומה Terumah do become
תרומה Terumah status as well. Okay. בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami
Bar Chama. רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama has a question on
it. אמר, קונם פירות האלו על פלוני Konam Peirot Ha'eilu Al Ploni
מהו בחילופיהן? Mahu Bechilufeihen? So he says fine, I get that if
I'm trying to make the fruits forbidden to myself, that חילופיהן Chilufeihen
should be forbidden. Okay, you can make whatever you want forbidden to
yourself, like great, so we can treat it with a certain level
of stringency, it can extend into other realms. But if you say
the fruits, these fruits are forbidden to פלוני, Ploni, someone else, so
then can this הלכה halacha, about חילופיהן, Chilufeihen, this extra חומרא Chumra
about חילופיהן, Chilufeihen, can that still apply? Okay. מי אמרינן Mi Amrinan
גבי דידיה Gabei Dilei הואיל ואדם אוסר פירות חברו על עצמו Ho'il
Ve'adam Oser Peirot Chavero Al Atzmo אדם אוסר דבר שלא בא לעולם
על עצמו. Adam Oser Davar Shelo Ba Le'olam Al Atzmo. So fine,
a person just like a person can make someone else's property forbidden
to himself, he can also make חילופיהן. Chilufeihen. חילופיהן Chilufeihen is דבר
שלא בא לעולם. Davar Shelo Ba Le'olam. It's something which you, which
almost in a certain sense doesn't even exist yet. But really what
it's saying is that right now it's totally someone else's money, it
hasn't yet been designated to this status yet, it has no connection
yet until the purchase is made. So in advance you're saying this
money which has not yet been spent for this purpose should already
have this איסור from right now, which is דבר שלא בא לעולם,
Davar Shelo Ba Le'olam it's something which doesn't yet exist. So he's
trying, so רמי בר חמא Rami Bar Chama is trying to compare
פירות
חברו Peirot Chavero and דבר שלא בא לעולם. Davar Shelo Ba Le'olam,
Just like a person has power to make someone else's property forbidden
to him, so too he could make דבר שלא בא לעולם davar
shelo ba l'olam. forbidden to him. Okay. גבי חברו Gabei Chavero הואיל
ואין אדם אוסר פירות חברו על חברו, Ho'il Ve'ein Adam Oser Peirot
Chavero Al Chavero,
just but by a case of someone else, you do not have
the power to make someone else's property forbidden to them, אין אדם
אוסר דבר שלא בא לעולם על חברו. Ein Adam Oser Davar Shelo
Ba Le'olam Al Chavero. So too you don't have the power to
make something which does not exist yet, something which has not yet
been designated to such and such purpose and therefore has no connection
to this, the money was not yet spent for those fruits, so
then you also would not be able to make that forbidden to
friends. Okay.
גבי חברו Gabei Chavero אדם אוסר פירות חברו על עצמו, Adam Oser
Peirot Chavero Al Atzmo, they're there now. אדם אוסר דבר שלא בא
לעולם Adam Oser Davar Shelo Ba Le'olam is not there now. So
you have these two separate concepts. I understand how you're framing it.
Okay, but they're both limitations on the power of the נודר Noder
to create this איסור. On the one hand because of אין אדם
אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, a person cannot make someone else's property forbidden
to them because you don't have rights to it, you can't control
it. חילופיהן Chilufeihen here, the way they're using דבר שלא בא לעולם,
davar shelo ba l'olam, something which does not yet exist, is also
saying it's too far removed, it's... too distant from you because what
is it? This is the money that would have been that will
be spent to buy the fruits from you, right? I have a
big bag of bananas that I made אסור asur to me with
a קונם. And now I go to sell them to someone. So
the money that he decides to spend would be חילופיהם. chilufeihem. But
right now when I took the נדר, neder,
he didn't plan to buy bananas at all, he maybe he didn't
even earn that money yet, who knows? It's floating around wherever. That
purchase is going to come much later and it will only be
designated as חילופי איסור, chilufei issur, the money that was spent to
buy the prohibited fruits, only later. And that's why it's דבר שלא
בא לעולם. davar shelo ba l'olam So again, it's outside of your
purview. You have no control. Question?
Is that not analogous to גידוליהם? giduleihem?
Ah, so the גידוליהם giduleihem kind of falls to the wayside here.
גידוליהם giduleihem becomes tricky and we'll get into that in just a
sec with the רמב"ם. Rambam.
Which is almost a similar situation to where he
dies and the ירושה. yerusha Okay.
Because you're saying it's kind of
going to eventually go into the next guy though he dies.
Right. So גידוליהם giduleihem is definitely an interesting how similar are חילופיהם
chilufeihem and גידוליהם giduleihem to each other and the parallel between מיתה
mita and ומכרו לאחר u-macharo le-acher is also fascinating. I didn't think
of that, but that's really cool point. I have to think about
that more.
How גידוליהם giduleihem and ירושה are in some sense parallel to each
other. Okay. So...
I mean I guess I still don't understand your answer. So what
are we trying to
say? To me, if I say your bananas are אסור asur to
me, right? Your bananas are there. I'm looking at them, let's say.
So I understand that. But if I say that like, you know,
דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam, you know, I don't
understand how like, you know, something here and now is is at
all analogous and it's not even there and never was at the
time.
Okay.
Is the question why can a person make דבר שלא בא לעולם
davar shelo ba l'olam אסור asur to himself? Yeah. So that's a
different meaning, okay, so it's explicit in the משנה. Mishnah. It's an
extra חומרא chumra that we have for when you take a נדר
against yourself, maybe again, that's in the משנה. Mishna He said חילופיהם
וגידוליהם. chilufeihem ve-giduleihem. So that's an interesting question about the power of
the נדר, but at least that's something that's reserved for a case
where a person is making something אסור asur. to himself. But I
would imagine, for example, if I say, Michael, you can't buy my
fruits, I make a נדר to prevent you from getting הנאה hana'ah
from me and then
you
do, are the חילופיהם chilufeihem now אסור asur to me as well?
The money that you spent for, you know, that's like an interesting
question as well.
We'd have to get into it a bit more, but at least
superficially at least this is saying in a case of making something
אסור asur to someone else, you have more limited rights than when
you're making something אסור assur, to yourself. When you make something אסור
assur. to yourself, you have control over
the object.
You can do whatever you want to yourself. You can make whatever
you want אסור. assur This is sort of the principle of הפה
שאסר הפה שהתיר ha-peh she-asar ha-peh she-hitir almost, that you can create
איסורים issurim for yourself. I mean that's the whole point of נדרים.
And so
that
would therefore be able to impact חילופיהם, chilufeihem, which is דבר שלא
בא לעולם, davar shelo ba l'olam it's something which doesn't yet exist,
as well as you can make someone else's property אסור assur to
you. However, by someone else, for a second, a second person, then
you don't have the power to make his own property forbidden to
him or even a third party forbidden to him. So too, you
don't have the power over דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba
l'olam, to make it אסור assur to him. In a certain sense
we can consider דבר שלא בא לעולם davar shelo ba l'olam. a
kind of third-party ownership. Something which does not yet exist is not
mine. Therefore I cannot make it forbidden to someone else. But I
can make it forbidden to myself, right? דבר שלא בא לעולם, davar
shelo ba le'olam. it doesn't exist at all, it has no ownership
because it doesn't exist or it has, so to say, no one
really has rights over it. So I could still make it forbidden
to myself just like I can make someone else's property forbidden to
me. But I cannot make it forbidden to someone else because it's
not under my control. Okay. So that's the first possibility. That's the
first possibility, is that we would make this analogy between, right? It's
one very long sentence, right?
מהו בחילופיהם, mahu be-chilufeihem, what should be the case of חילופיהם? chilufeihem?
ומי אמרינן גבי דיליה הואיל ואדם אוסר פירות חבירו על עצמו אדם
אוסר דבר שלא בא לעולם על עצמו. u-mi amrinan gabi dileh ho'il
ve-adam oser peirot chaveiro al atzmo adam oser davar shelo ba l'olam
al atzmo. So the case of the person making it forbidden to
himself. גבי חבירו הואיל ואין אדם אוסר פירות חבירו על חבירו אין
אדם אוסר דבר שלא בא לעולם על חבירו. gabi chaveiro ho'il ve-ein
adam oser peirot chaveiro al chaveiro ein adam oser davar shelo ba
l'olam al chaveiro. So that's what we just read. או דילמא o
dilma alternatively,
so what's the other possibility? או דילמא משום דחילופין כגידולים דמי. o
dilma mishum de-chilufin ke-gidulim dami. Okay. Or are חילופין chilufin like גידולים,
gidulim, meaning that just like the גידולים gidulim are forbidden presumably to
whomever, so then that would apply however it would across the board.
It wouldn't be limited just to if I would make it to
me. But it would be in all the cases, right? וגידוליהם ve-giduleihem
again are also something which is דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar shelo
ba le'olam. I haven't yet planted the fruits, it hasn't yet given
forth any produce. Okay. So לא שנא, la shena, it doesn't matter,
לא שנא הוא ולא שנא חבירו. la shena hu ve-la shena chaveiro.
It shouldn't apply, it shouldn't differ between whether it's a person for
himself or a person for his friend. So those are two possibilities.
Number one, either חילופיהם chilufeihem should be like a case of someone
else's property and therefore the prohibition should only work for me but
not if it's for someone else. Or חילופיהם chilufeihem are like גידוליהם.
giduleihem. The money that is spent in exchange for the forbidden fruit
is similar to the produce that would grow out of this fruit
and therefore it should apply across the board. Because it's mentioned in
the same Mishna together, because they're both דבר שלא בא לעולם. davar
shelo ba le'olam.
That's what I'm trying to say, they're not דבר שלא בא לעולם.
Why?
Well, the money is, the money exists.
The fruit of the fruit isn't there, you know.
Right, well that's the point. Right, גידוליהם giduleihem is also דבר שלא
בא לעולם. The produce doesn't exist.
No, I'm trying to tell you חילופיהם chilufeihem is דבר שבא לעולם,
davar sheba le'olam, גידוליהם giduleihem is not.
Why? If I say this is the fruit that's אסור, assur,
when I take the נדר, I made the fruit אסור. assur, But
the money that will then later be spent in exchange for the
fruit has not yet been designated to that purpose. So it can't
be included in the נדר because it doesn't exist as money spent
for, money used to buy אסור assur. fruit.
I guess we'll see a reason or maybe not, I don't know,
but to say that like you know since like money was maybe
only minted or versus money that's already there, you know, money's at
least there, you know what I mean?
Yeah, the physical object of the money exists but money spent for
אסור assur bananas doesn't exist because it never had that status yet.
It wasn't used for that purpose.
Yeah, but I see like again, a certain amount of you know,
tangible...
Right, again, the object exists but not an object with this status.
Fruit will grow from the tree, but is it guaranteed you're going
to sell what you have?
And it doesn't... it doesn't exist yet in that sense. Right. If
you would call it
חילופי פירות איסור, chilufei peirot issur, it doesn't have that status yet.
Okay, so that's the question, we have two possibilities. So אמר רב
אחא בר מניומי, Amar Rav Acha Bar Minyumi, so רב אחא בר
מניומי Rav Acha Bar Minyumi has an answer to our question. What
should be the case? תא שמע האומר לאשתו Ta shema ha'omer leishto
קונם שאני נהנה
ליך,
konam she'ani
neheneh lach, לווים ובעלי חובות באים ונפרעים. lovin uba'alei chovot ba'im venifra'im.
A case is a person says to his wife קונם שאני נהנה
ליך, konam she'ani neheneh lach, I cannot benefit you. Okay, then the
creditors can come and extract the debt. Okay, that's the case. So
first of all, we have to note the fact that the ר"ן
says at least it has to be before נישואין nisu'in because otherwise
this is going against the תנאי tnai of the כתובה ketubah that
the husband has the obligation to pay debts for his spouse. And
so if that's the case, then you wouldn't be able to take
this נדר because again it's contradicting the obligation of the כתובה. ketubah.
However, if it were before נישואין, nisu'in, then this person could have
made this נדר. The נדר is I'm not going to benefit you,
and therefore
when the wife has certain debts, nonetheless לווים ובעלי חובות באים ונפרעים,
lovin uba'alei chovot ba'im venifra'im,
they can still come and extract their debt. So now we have
a question: מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? How does this work? בעלי חובות
נפרעים? Ba'alei chovot nifra'im?
We had that before, right? מבריח ארי. Mavriach ari. Didn't we have
that? You're just מבריח
ארי, mavriach
ari,
you're
not really נהנה them, but like you're just like you know dismissing
a creditor as opposed to chasing a lion off property, right? Remember
that? Right.
But this case, the case here is that
the wife has a debt, right?
I pay somebody else's support, right? As a guy goes to מדינת
הים, medinat hayam, right, and he needs to support his wife. I
can still do that because I'm not נהנה him, I'm just you
know מבריח mavriach a creditor, right? He's a creditor to the husband
and I'm just chasing a lion away.
Right.
I think that is in the end how it ends up working.
Right? I mean they're saying how does this work, right? So מאי
טעמא בעלי חובות נפרעים? mai ta'ama ba'alei chovot nifra'im? How can the
creditors come and extract their debt? לאו משום דחילופין, lav mishum dechilufin,
right? Aren't those then in exchange? Meaning the wife borrowed money and
now the creditor comes and the husband is paying it off. So
that's like חילופי איסור chilufei issur in some sense because it's the
money that was spent for paying back the debt that the wife
did and that's benefiting her, right? So לאו כגידולין דמי? lav kegidulin
dami? So doesn't that sound like חילופין chilufin should not apply like
גידולין? gidulin? Because חילופין chilufin would be permitted to the wife
and גידולין... gidulin... I think this is the same case that you're
talking about almost. Right, it's saying it is permitted for the husband
to pay off the creditors, right?
But not because of חילופין וגידולין, chilufin ugedulin, because...
no, but that's a proof that חילופין chilufin are not like גידולין.
gidulin. Because גידולין gidulin would be אסור assur even to the wife.
But חילופין chilufin in a case of a second party, where the
husband made the wife אסור, assur so then we would say oh
well maybe חילופין chilufin should apply because, or sorry, shouldn't apply, sorry,
if חילופין chilufin would apply to the wife like גידולין, gidulin, then
the husband would not... able to pay off the wife's debts, right?
So here, the fact that he can pay off, he says, אה
לאו משום דחילופין לאו כגידולין דמי, Ah lav mishum de-chilufin lav ke-gidulin
dami, so doesn't that sound like חילופין chilufin are not like גידולין,
gidulin, meaning that because the husband made his wife אסור, asur so
that's another person and therefore the only thing you have control over
is the הנאה hana'ah itself but not over the חילופי הנאה. chilufei
hana'ah. Okay. אמר רבא. So רבא says, דילמא לכתחילה הוא.
dilma lechatchila hu. Okay.
דלא. de-lo. ואי עבד עבד. ve-im avad avad. לכתחילה lechatchila he cannot,
meaning cannot do what? Cannot use the חילופין. chilufin. It's only לכתחילה,
lechatchila, but דיעבד עבד. de-avad avad. If he already did it, then
it would still work, meaning that the חילופין chilufin are not אסור.
asur Why? Sounds like because at that point it's already two steps
removed. That once it's that you you paid off the loan, then
the הנאה hana'ah that the wife gets from the loan being paid
off is already a further step removed than from there. Okay. אלא
תא שמע. Ella tashma. Therefore, רבא needs to bring a different proof
because he doesn't think that this is a substantial proof for the
fact דחילופין לאו כגידולין דמי, de-chilufin lav ke-gidulin dami, that חילופין chilufin
should not apply to the wife. Rather he says, המקדש בערלה אינה
מקודשת. hamikadesh be-orlah eina mikudeshet. What if a person tries to use
fruits of ערלה orlah as קידושין kiddushin money? To get married you
need a פרוטה, prutah, שוה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, and fruit is worth
שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. However, ערלה orlah is אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah,
ערלה orlah is the fruit from the first three years of a
fruit-bearing tree. So המקדש בערלה אינה מקודשת hamikadesh be-orlah eina mikudeshet because
it is אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah, So we can draw an analogy
between איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah of ערלה orlah and איסורי הנאה issurei
hana'ah of נדרים, okay? The הנאה hana'ah, that the wife would get
from the ערלה orlah or the הנאה hana'ah, the wife would get
from something which the husband said you have a נדר to not
get הנאה hana'ah from me. So the משנה—the Mishnah. גמרא in נדרים—in
קידושין Kiddushin says, המקדש בערלה אינה מקודשת. hamikadesh be-orlah eina mikudeshet. If
you try to use ערלה orlah as your קידושין kiddushin money, it
doesn't work because it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah So the wife can't
get any הנאה hana'ah from it so what even if she accepts
the fruit as a gift, technically because it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah
so she doesn't get the שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah.
Getting married is הנאה.
hana'ah Getting married is a certain הנאה, hana'ah for example all the—many
examples from the second and third פרק perek of קידושין Kiddushin talk
about what if the wife says to the—the fiancée says to her
fiancé, 'Do a dance for me and the הנאה hana'ah. that I
get from watching you dance will be the קידושין kiddushin money,' or
things like that. Even cases
of—the most extreme case is the case of אדם חשוב Adam Chashuv
in the first פרק. perek. The wife says, 'You are so חשוב,
chashuv, you're, you know, you're the President, you're the Senator, something, it's
so—or you're a big billionaire—the fact that you would accept a gift
from me is worth a פרוטה prutah to me because it shows
that you you like me enough.' So the fact that you're willing
to accept a gift—so the wife gives the husband a gift and
the הנאה hana'ah that she gets that he would accept her gift
is—is הנאה hana'ah for her as well. So there are a number
of interesting cases in קידושין Kiddushin soon we'll be there in a
few months, right? So they'll—they'll be waiting for us.
I was trying to think of the word for חשוב chashuv in
my head.
Okay. המקדש בערלה אינה מקודשת. hamikadesh be-orlah eina mikudeshet. So if you
try to use ערלה orlah as קידושין kiddushin money, it doesn't work.
However, מכרן וקידש בדמיהם הרי זו מקודשת. micharan ve-kidesh bi-dmeihem harei zo
mekudeshet. What if you sold the ערלה orlah even though it's אסור
asur בהנאה, be'hana'ah you sold ערלה orlah illegally and then you took
the money that you made from selling the fruit and you used
that as קידושין kiddushin money, הרי זו מקודשת. harei zo mekudeshet. It
should—it would work. Ah, so that's a problem, why? Because that's חילופיהם.
chilufeihem. So it sounds like
חילופי איסור chilufei issur would be useful, would be permitted. Okay. הכא
נמי לכתחילה הוא דלא ואי עבד עבד מיהו. hacha nami lechatchila hu
de-lo ve-im avad avad miho. No, לכתחילה lechatchila wouldn't work, but once
you did it, it counts as מקודשת mekudeshet and there it's done.
So a few other points here. Number one, the
the case of ערלה orlah is different because here it's not that
the הנאה is going to the wife directly. Once again, we see
that if it's two steps removed—I sold the ערלה orlah and then
I give the money to the woman—then that's two steps
removed, that's also—that would—it would work. However, the case of the paying
off the loan also is a two steps removed. The woman borrowed
the money and then I have to pay off the creditor. So
it's not a direct הנאה from husband to the wife, it's—it's something
more triangular. And because of that, that's what it's saying here לכתחילה
lechatchila and דיעבד עבד, de-avad avad, that sort of the בדיעבד bedi'avad
and לכתחילה lechatchila part of this that at least לכתחילה lechatchila it's
better to avoid that kind of הנאה, it still is a—still is
a הנאה, but בדיעבד bedi'avad because it's two steps removed, it's not
really caught in the נדר the same way.
Is there a distinction made between the legal act that the wife
did and the illegal act of selling the ערלה? orlah?
I think that that is part of it, yes.
No, I'm saying... I'm saying, you're saying it works even though it's
illegal, right? But is there—so no distinction's made between doing an illegal
act
like—well, selling the ערלה orlah was illegal.
Yes, to a מצוה mitzvah with something that he—like if he stole
the four species. Right. It's an invalid מצוה when you shake it,
right?
Right, so you'll say something like
מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah. The fact that you're getting married
using something that was from אסור asur from ערלה, orlah, that's also
an interesting question. I suppose part of the answer to that is
that once you sell the ערלה, orlah, the money is still whatever
money you have. It's money. Money is money.
It's a good question. I'll have to think about that.
Yeah, that's a very good question.
Okay, one other question here about the ערלה orlah is ערלה orlah
you're required to burn it, right? So fine, you want to say
מקדש בערלה אינה מקודשת, mekadesh b'orlah einah mekudeshet, what if I give
a huge barrel of ערלה? orlah? So even if the wife then
burns all the fruits, then the ashes would still be worth a
פרוטה, prutah, shouldn't that work for קידושין? kiddushin? So we have a
principle based on קרבנות korbanos as well, that anything which has to
be destroyed by burning, נשרפים, nisrafim, the ashes attain a new status.
The ashes say פנים חדשות באו לכאן, panim chadashos bau l'kan, it's
a new object. So it's not—this isn't ערלה orlah anymore. The act
of burning removed it from the ערלה orlah and it's not only
not ערלה, orlah, but it's also not the same thing that the
husband gave to the wife.
So giving a huge sack of ערלה orlah fruits and then she
would burn them and their ash would be worth a פרוטה, prutah,
it still wouldn't work for the קידושין. kiddushin. That's an interesting observation
as well.
Yes, and also about the פרה
אדומה?
parah
adumah? In terms of ashes a new status?
I guess all kinds of—and that whole question, the mystery of how
this gets handed down from the טמא tamei to the טהור tahor
to the טמא tamei and so forth.
So what you're saying that since it's burned it's a new status,
so therefore so too someone is becoming טמא tamei to טהור tahor
to the question.
פרה
אדומה parah adumah is a pet topic of mine. It's one of
my favorite things to study. I have plenty to say about what
you just said, but I can't go into it now. No, no,
no, definitely didn't figure it out, but okay. One other interesting thing
from the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam in פרק ה' Perek Hey
of הלכות נדרים, Hilchos Nedarim, הלכה ז'. Halacha Zayin. The רמב"ם Rambam
says אסר בנו בהנאה. asar bno behana'ah. This is going back to
the case we had in עמוד א'. Amud Alef. A person makes
his son אסור assur to get הנאה from him.
ואמר ואם היה בן בני זה תלמיד חכם יקנה בני זה נכסיי
כדי להקנותם לבני הרי זה מותר. v'amar v'im hayah ben bni zeh
talmid chacham yikneh bni zeh nechasai k'dei l'haknotam libni harei zeh mutar.
Fine, that's an interesting case. Also, if he becomes a תלמיד חכם
talmid chacham then it's fine. Okay, but now going to הלכה ח'.
Halacha Chet. זה הבן האסור בירושת אביו אם נתן ירושת אביו לאחיו
או לבניו הרי זה מותר. zeh haben ha'asur biyerushat aviv im natan
yerushat aviv l'achav o livnav harei zeh mutar. The son who is
אסור assur in
ירושת אביו, yerushat aviv, if he gave ירושת אביו yerushat aviv to
his brother or to his sons, it is מותר. mutar. That's permitted.
So again, that was a case from the בבא קמא. And the
ראב"ד Ra'avad has a problem.
I don't understand what he's giving if he can't have it.
So he's giving up his rights to
it, meaning—not giving up, he doesn't have any rights to it.
Well, he has enough rights—again, what the ר"ן and the רשב"א disagree.
The ר"ן says really he could own the property as long as
he doesn't get any benefit once he owns it. Or he's just
giving up on his rights and saying, hey you, you can take
that.
That's not enough of a—Giving up on his rights, he couldn't take
it? No, if I said you can't inherit—so I have two kids.
I say to one, you can't inherit, right? Which implies obviously the
other one inherits everything. So what you're saying is unless the first
one gives up his rights, the second one doesn't inherit?
No, the second one—the second one retains enough rights to pass it
on to his children or the other brothers and things like that.
Meaning just because it was—meaning it wasn't saying this portion of the
inheritance is אסור assur בהנאה to you. You're saying you're
אסור בהנאה from me. Now comes time to inherit, there's still—he still
has some connection to the inheritance and then he can kind of
pass it on to somebody else. That's again—Right, but that's what I'm
saying.
I don't understand that.
Meaning he didn't get any הנאה from it. He didn't ever really
own it and even according to the ר"ן he could own it,
he just can't get any other הנאה from it. Okay, the ראב"ד
Ra'avad disagrees with the רמב"ם. Rambam. The
ראב"ד Ra'avad says אסר בנו בהנאה זו בן הבן מותר בהן אם
יהיה בן תלמיד חכם כמו שנאמר. asar bno behana'ah zo ben haben
mutar bahen im yihiyeh ben talmid chacham k'mo shene'emar. Okay, so אמר
אברהם. amar Avraham. The ראב"ד Ra'avad says ומה צריך לתנאו? u'mah tzarich
litna'o? Why does he need this condition? והלא בלא תנאי אנו אומרים
יתן לבניו ולאחיו, v'halo belo tenai anu omrim yiten livnav v'le'achav, right?
Why should he then make a תנאי, tenai, a תנאי, tenai, a
condition in the נדר that
if—if you have this grandson then it should be מותר? mutar? Why
do you have to mention that explicitly? The next הלכה, הלכה ח'
Halacha Chet that the רמב"ם Rambam says, he even says that the
son can give it to his own children. So the ראב"ד Ra'avad
sort of doesn't understand how this is fitting together. Okay, אבל אם
לא צריך
לומר אם נאמר קנה על
מנת להקנות קנה או לא. aval im lo tzorich
lomar im ne'emar kanah al
menat l'haknot kanah o lo. אלא אם יוכל אדם למשכנו באותן נכסים
או לא, ela im yuchal adam l'mashkeno b'otan nechasim o lo, אבל
אם יאסור בנו באותן נכסים aval im yosir b'no b'otan nechasim לא
צריכא לומר lo tzricha lomar שאינו נאסר כלל. she'eino ne'esar klal.
And so, sorry, I put a note here about what I wanted
to say but... oh, that the רמב״ם Rambam says, oh, that the
רמב״ם Rambam in the last line here... did I not?
I'm sorry, I forgot what I wanted to say about this and
now it's not coming back to me. Okay. I'm sorry. Let's go
on to the next משנה. Mishnah And we'll start with the next
משנה Mishnah and maybe even a little bit of גמרא and then
we'll leave for tomorrow for שבת. Shabbos. Okay. The משנה Mishnah says:
הריני עליך חרם. Hareini alecha cherem. I am to you חרם, cherem,
presumably saying: I, my property, is totally forbidden
בהנאה to you. המודר אסור. Hamudar asur. הרי את עלי חרם. Harei
at alai cherem. You are to me חרם. cherem. הנודר אסור. Hanoder
asur. Okay? So that's almost a standard formula of נדרים. It doesn't
seem so different except we're introducing now the word חרם cherem rather
than using some of the other words we've used, קונם and things
like that. Okay. הנודר אסור. Hanoder asur. הריני עליך ואת עלי. Hareini
alecha ve'at alai. So: I am to you and you are to
me. שניהם אסורים, shneihem asurim, ושניהם מותרים, ve'shneihem mutarim,
שניהם אסורים, shneihem asurim, ושניהם מותרים בדבר של
עולי בבל. u'shneihem mutarim be'davar shel Olei Bavel. And they are both
permitted to use things which are for עולי בבל. Olei Bavel. עולי
בבל, Olei Bavel, things of עולי בבל, Olei Bavel, it's talking about
things which are, sort of say, public use kinds of things. שהפקירום
עולי בבל לכל ישראל. she'hefkirum Olei Bavel l'chol Yisrael. That the people
who came from בבל Bavel brought all these things and said that
this property is for everyone. So because it's for everyone, then it's
not that each of them had a right over it to the
other, but because it was almost sort of public use or was
given over הפקר hefker to everyone, then that's enough to say that
both of them would still be permitted even if they each had
made each other's property forbidden to each other. Yes.
This would have huge consequences in ישראל Yisrael today because almost all
land is communally owned.
Okay. And you're saying then that a person still wouldn't have the
power to אסר aser his land to someone else because it doesn't
really belong... I don't know the details of land ownership in ישראל.
Yisrael. I do know that there's something like that, right, it's like
75 or 95 percent of the country is owned by קק״ל Kakal
and then how it was then on leasing terms, something like that.
I don't know the details. Okay. ואסורים בדבר של אותה העיר. ve'asurim
be'davar shel ota ha'ir. But they are both prohibited to use things
of the city. This is going into something we talked about earlier
about the עיר, ir, about the communal ownership in a city, similar
to the בית הכנסת beit haknesset we talked about. The שול, shul,
the שול shul is sort of a shared public space and that
has almost shareholders, it has a corporate structure in some sense. So
here too, things which are owned from the whole city, because they
really do belong to each of them, they live in the city,
they both pay the taxes for the city or whatever, they're both
shareholders in ownership of that. So if they each said חרם cherem
to each other, then that would make the city itself, the things
which are publicly owned in the city, אסור to both of them.
But things of עולי בבל, Olei Bavel, which are totally הפקר hefker
to all of ישראל, Yisrael, then no one has the right to
make that אסור each to each other because they're not really owners.
They're still sort of הפקר hefker to the whole ישראל. Yisrael. Okay.
ואיזהו דבר של עולי בבל? v'eizehu davar shel Olei Bavel? What are
things which are considered things from עולי בבל? Olei Bavel? כגון הר
הבית והעזרות והבור שבאמצע הדרך. k'gon Har HaBayit ve'ha'azarot ve'habor she'be'emtza ha'derech.
הר הבית, Har HaBayit, הר הבית Har HaBayit is basically owned by
the entire Jewish people, and therefore, when two people take הנאה one
from the other, it wouldn't be... it wouldn't make it that הר
הבית Har HaBayit would be אסור to them, because neither of them
has the power to אסר aser הר הבית Har HaBayit to the
other. Or the next: הר הבית והעזרות, Har HaBayit ve'ha'azarot, העזרות, ha'azarot,
the extensions of הר הבית. Har HaBayit. So הר הבית Har HaBayit
itself was then expanded, not just the Temple precincts itself, but the
outer courtyards as well. In some sense we have to ask: well,
why are those sort of two separate statuses? Why is that important?
Maybe we'll go into it a little bit more tomorrow. והבור שבאמצע
הדרך, ve'habor she'be'emtza ha'derech, and a well or a hole that is
in the street, this really means like a rest stop, a place
to water your animals, a place that's along the road. The עולי
בבל Olei Bavel we often see mention of the fact that when
they were coming on עולי הרגל, olei ha'regel, they would have to
bring all the different animals with them and have to set up
watering holes and things like that. Yes. Charlie?
Some of this... how do you benefit from the Temple Mount?
Okay, so part of it is that we already said that maybe
there's an opinion that walking somewhere counts as הנאה.
But it's אסור to walk through the Temple Mount...
oh, but even to go up there and walk...
you have to leave by the same exit that you... you can't
use a
shortcut...
but maybe it's because you're allowed...
you're bringing in a sacrifice or you're observing something at the Temple.
So
is
that separate from the sanctuary, the
Temple Mount?
So I'll have to see. It's a good question. I'll try to
look into what what הנאה you would be getting from the הר
הבית Har Habayit that they're concerned about. Okay, and what about דבר
של עולי בבל? Davar Shel Oleh Bavel? So a דבר של עולי
בבל, Davar Shel Oleh Bavel, עולי בבל Oleh Bavel is הר הבית
Har Habayit and the עזרות azarot and a well in the middle
of the road, meaning like a rest stop along the highway. ואיזו
דבר של אותה העיר? Ve'eizu Davar Shel Otah Ha'ir? What is something
that belongs to the city, public use space in the city? כגון
הרחבה, Kegon harachavah, the town square, והמרחץ vehamerchatz
and the bathhouse, but this is a public bathhouse, not privately owned.
Often we see privately owned bathhouse, public owned bathhouse. This is a
publicly owned bathhouse. ובית הכנסת U'beit Haknesset
and the שול, shul, והתיבה והספרים vehateivah vehasfarim
and the ark and the books, but books mean ספרי תורה Sifrei
Torah and also the ספרי נביאים וכתובים. Sifrei Nevi'im u'Ketuvim. ספרים Sfarim
in משנה Mishnah language.
So I don't see so I say you can't get הנאה from
me, you can't walk on streets now?
No, so the street is also the street, that's the point.
You can't walk
there.
Oh right right, because because I'm a joint owner in the street.
Exactly. If I say חרם... cherem... that's ridiculous.
That's why it's a dangerous thing to get involved with this נדר,
right.
But I mean as a matter of public policy you should be
considered null and void. Like you know like I don't understand how
you can possibly do that. I'm forbidding you to go outside for
the rest of your life?
Well this is something that we saw already from the case of
the שותפים, shutafim, right? This is the רבנן's Rabbanan position that if
you say we have two people living in a courtyard and they
say
we're going to leave this specific business deal with each other, fine.
But like so I can just be pissed off at you and
I can say alright you are now אסור to go out from
your house because I'm now forbidding you the sidewalks, the streets, whatever
it is. How can he do that? Like it doesn't make sense.
Get what I'm saying?
Yeah I get what you're saying, it's a very extreme position but
that's really what it's saying about communal ownership really that everyone has
a share. Now you might want to say oh
maybe I would object it I actually think it should be the
same thing as עולי בבל. Oleh Bavel.
Okay so maybe so then the question is between our cities nowadays
are we really living in a של אותה העיר Shel Otah Ha'ir
kind of situation or are we living in עולי בבל Oleh Bavel
situation? Which road? Interstate highway is different from the state highway is
different from the municipal highways, you know all those kind of questions.
For sure it's very radical but that's what it's saying about ownership.
If it's communal isn't the person also prohibiting
something on something that's owned by the person who's being prohibited?
Ah so that's also a very good question, right? Isn't it אין
אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, which means one person even though you
have a portion ownership in this, so does someone else. So that
would basically be what רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar Ben Yaakov
would say. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar Ben Yaakov who we
saw in the first משנה Mishnah. in the פרק, perek, his ברירה
breira position is to say
look, fact
like I also own part of this and I have enough rights
to get through.
Yeah then why isn't רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar Ben Yaakov
disagreeing over here then?
That's also an interesting question about the משנה. Mishnah Let's just go
through the rest of this משנה Mishnah and we'll try to go
over it again tomorrow when I'll try to pull together some more
pieces to bring it all together.
Fine, I apologize for not having prepared this משנה Mishnah. the best
of the best that I could have.
It
is on the next דף daf so you're
it is on the next דף, daf, that's what I'm saying we're
trying to go ahead and then you know so
if we're going to backtrack then
well backtrack a touch a little bit here and then you know
we don't want to waste the time so let's just finish the
משנה. Mishna Okay, and another thing which counts as דבר של אותה
העיר, Davar Shel Otah Ha'ir, yeah.
Let me see if I can figure out an answer to this
question of mine because like I just can't fathom I can't get
my arms around this.
About which? About the fact that it's so radical, that it's so
extreme that you have the power to אסור someone to leave their
house basically? Yeah. Right. Look into that, that's a good question. Again,
נדרים are tough stuff, it's
I understand it's totally mine you can't come into my house, but
I'm saying you can't go
anywhere.
Right. Right. Unless you move. Right.
How do you get out?
Yeah. Move to a different city, right.
You'd have to get a helicopter.
Or התרת נדרים.
hatarat nedarim.
Right.
Okay so we'll see. Okay. והכותב חלקו לנשיא. Vehakotev chelko l'nasi. What
if someone writes over his portion to the נשיא, Nasi, presumably someone
sort of signing away their ownership but it's going to be explained
later on in the גמרא so we'll do that tomorrow. Okay. רבי
יהודה אומר אחד הכותב לנשיא ואחד הכותב להדיוט. Rabbi Yehuda omer echad
hakotev l'nasi ve'echad hakotev l'hedyot.
It's no different to sign over your ownership either to the נשיא
Nasi the governor or כותב חלקו לנשיא kotev chelko l'nasi sounds like
it means you sign over whatever part of the city you own
to the נשיא. Nasi. No, that it would remain prohibited because the
נשיא Nasi is really like the governor and since it's whatever you
would transfer over to the governor still remains in the municipal ownership
so that still would remain joint
ownership.
But the Artscroll notes, this is Artscroll that says
in this concept of writing his share to the נשיא, Nasi, yeah.
It says when two people forbade their property upon one another and
thus rendered each other forbidden to use municipal facilities they can lift
this aspect of the prohibition by writing a document in which they
cede their shares in this in these facilities to a third party.
And the נשיא Nasi is an ideal third
party.
Right, so if you would sign over your property.
But what if I don't want to? But what if you don't
want to? Then right. But again, I'm with you and you know
you're never going to be out of your house again, ha, I
got you.
But then we have ways,
oh yeah, well then you can אסור it to me.
I mean like, we have ways of forcing, you know, those are
part of the question about what's going on here, right, for sure.
Okay. רבי יהודה אומר אחד כותב לנשיא ואחד כותב להדיוט. Rabbi Yehuda
Omer echad kotev l'Nasi v'echad kotev l'hedyot. You could write it either
to whomever you want, either to the נשיא Nasi or to just
someone generally. מה בין כותב לנשיא לכותב להדיוט? Ma bein kotev l'Nasi
l'kotev l'hedyot?
What's the difference then? שהכותב לנשיא אין צריך לזכות ולהדיוט צריך לזכות.
Shehakotev l'Nasi ein tzarich lizkot v'lahedyot tzarich lizkot.
So a נשיא, Nasi, it has to, it doesn't have to be
done in such a way that he can actually gain the ownership,
but with a הדיוט, hedyot, the person has to really be there
in order to be קונה koneh
this, this rights. A person has to be present or whatever way
to be able to make that acquisition. Okay. וחכמים אומרים אחד זה
ואחד זה צריכים לזכות. Vachachamim omrim echad zeh v'echad zeh tzrichim lizkot.
Both of them have to actually be there to acquire it. לא
דיברו בנשיא אלא
בהווה. Lo dibru b'Nasi ela b'hoveh. They're just saying נשיא Nasi because
that's a convenient thing to do. Meaning there's no halachic difference between
the נשיא Nasi and the הדיוט, hedyot, just that that's a realistic
or likely way of doing it. רבי יהודה אומר אין אנשי גליל
צריכים לכתוב. Rabbi Yehuda Omer ein anshei Galil tzrichim lichtov. In the
גליל, Galil, the people don't have to do it this way. You
don't have to sign over your rights. Why? שכבר כתבו אבותיהם על
ידיהם. Shekvar katvu avoteihem al yadeihem.
Because already the land agreements in the גליל Galil were signed over
in a similar way generations ago by their ancestors, so then it's
not even applicable anymore because at this point you're totally stuck. Okay,
so let's stop here for now. We'll go back over this משנה
tomorrow שבת Shabbat afternoon and then move forward with the גמרא. And
we will finish the פרק. Perek.
Socialism? Socialism.
Yeah.
What about socialism?
Well the, the government owns everything. They wrote everything.